hi it's sunday morning again and today
we're going to talk about the history of
vanilla ice cream so
fancy graphics
let's go
we're going to start talking about
vanilla itself now this was first used
by the mexican people of modern day
mexico vanilla made its way to spain via
the spanish conquistadors in the 1500s
it was used in a drink which consisted
of cocoa beans vanilla
corn water and honey
and the drink made its way to europe by
the early 1600s in 1602 hugh morgan the
apothecary of the queen elizabeth ii
said that vanilla should then be used
separately from the cocoa but what was
the drink that they made it was a form
of
posol which is a fermented corn drink
made popular in tabasco the fermented
drink was used to control digestive
issues originally just as an fyi
vanilla was a rarity for most of its
history and it wasn't until 1837 when
belgian botanist charles francois
antoine marine discovered how to
artificially pollinate vanilla plants
but it wasn't viable commercially it was
1841 when edmund albious proved hand
pollination was feasible and that method
then spread across the world so with the
basics about vanilla let's move on to
the ice cream we can see actual ice
cream in the 1300s in yuan period it
wasn't until late 1600s though that the
french started adding vanilla to their
ice cream recipes
and that's when the french vanilla ice
cream was born
apparently thomas jefferson brought
vanilla ice cream to the us during the
1700s when he created his own vanilla
ice cream recipe but what did they make
ice cream in in those times
these style of ice cream machines are
still available today but you do need
again the ice and salt to act as the
cooling medium
they are actually very good but a little
bit time consuming so now we know some
of the basic information about vanilla
and ice cream let's knock a couple up
and get them out on the table and see
first we're going to do i should
probably do a split screen
on
the left we'll do a french vanilla
custard and on the right we'll do an
american style philly vanilla ice cream
so stick around and we'll see what
they're like when they're done
for the french vanilla ice cream
put your dry ingredients and your milk
into a pan and that includes your egg
yolks and bring them up to 82 degrees c
while stirring constantly
at that point you can add your vanilla
bean or you can take it off the heat add
your cream and then add your vanilla
bean caviar let that sit in a container
in the fridge for four hours for that
flavor to really build
philly style ice cream is much easier to
make you can put all your ingredients in
a pan if you like but again i like to
just use the milk and dry ingredients to
start with
bring it all up to a warm temperature
just so everything's dissolved take it
off the heat
add your cream and your vanilla extract
and again put it in the fridge for a few
hours to chill down
here we go
we have french vanilla
and the philly style i have just called
this one philly vanilli because i'm an
idiot like that
i'm gonna get some scoops on there and
we'll compare the two and then wrap this
up
[Music]
two different vanillas i don't make
vanilla ice cream often i find it
a little bit you know vanilla in flavor
i find a little bit boring
but
whenever i do make it especially the the
french vanilla ice cream the custard
version
i always think to myself i should make
it more often because it's really good
the philly style so a couple of things
to mention philly style ice cream
doesn't keep as long in the freezer as
the custard types or non-stabilized
versions of ice cream
it's best if you a eat it out of the
machine but if you do have to put it in
the freezer make sure you cover the top
with something and eat it within you
know a couple of days but
the custard-based ice cream will last a
lot longer and if you do use a
stabilizer that will help it last even
longer still so let's just try a bit of
each and then we'll talk about it after
[Music]
philly vanilli
the philly style one
it's obviously very nice it tastes great
it tastes like vanilla it's a very
natural vanilla flavor because obviously
it's a good quality vanilla extract
it's quite
plain
that would be a great base if you're
going to add you know some kind of swirl
or add in something like that you can do
that or you can make a sweet cream base
of flavorless base
but it does lack
some of that
you know juan aviv of
the french
style
vanilla custard it tastes no obviously
it tastes kind of like custard that's
the plan that that's why it was made
like it was originally
it's rich
it's creamy the egg yolks offer the
emulsification that a lot of ice cream
benefits from
it makes that vanilla pop as well
now interestingly vanilla can also be
used to boost other flavors so if you
just add a little bit of vanilla extract
to some things it will do the same as
salt and a lot of other extracts will do
the same thing as long as you don't add
too much of it to overpower the taste it
will boost the other flavors that are in
there i used some almond extract in
our previous video the vegan pistachio
i'll put a link below
and that just boosted that pistachio
flavor and enough without that
overtaking and that's what vanilla does
classic flavor vanilla ice cream don't
be afraid to make it i obviously make
lots of weird and wonderful add-in heavy
ben and jerry's style ice creams
but i will make that french vanilla
custard ice cream again i should make it
more often it's really really nice
well hopefully this gave you just a
little bit of insight into where vanilla
ice cream came from there's a lot more
information out there about it so get
googling have a look and
try both of them
there's no
perfect solution to ice cream make what
suits you
make what tastes right
for you and most of all
bloody well enjoy it
thanks very much for watching don't
forget to like and subscribe
next week we're gonna make the tim tam
ice cream
that was voted for on our facebook page
i'll put a link just here in the screen
so get over and join in on conversation
take care
[Music]